foreign
[Music]
for the year 2023 the Gregorian year
2023. so we're going to take a bunch of
questions today we're going to deal with
some geopolitics more history today and
maybe even some science depending on how
much time we have I've selected a whole
lot of questions and let's see how many
we can cover and before we do that let
me see who all is there let me greet you
all
who's in the live chat I can see the guy
anshul
CEO of Sigma grind
seti just ate tripty crazy brain sanjoy
Joe Stalin bhavna Victoria
vasal of USA darshan vineet manmad
anjana
Mishra
video
Albert Davis
physicist hello ujjwal Alpha pratham
socialist
Soviet Union father of Pakistan Kushi
Rani adrish
and lots and lots and other people vasal
of USA aryaman somnath Bunty Karthik
priyanshi mukul and lots of people thank
you all for being on this live stream so
let's get into the questions without any
further Ado what are the questions let's
see
Rohan says did you achieve all your
goals you decided to at the start of
2022 I did not achieve all of the goals
I had thought of achieving at the start
of 2022 and the what's interesting is
that I achieved certain things I had not
even thought of achieving achieving in
2022. so as you as see the thing is
without a goal you can't score as a
cliche goes so so you need to have some
goals a set of goals not too many not
too few a certain set of goals and then
try to work towards that as as much as
you can I obviously worked very very
hard I did not take almost any time off
I did not that wasn't I wasn't slacking
I worked really hard and when you do
that new opportunities come your way a
new uh achievements sometimes are
unlocked like they say in gaming so I
did not achieve all of the goals see
when you start working towards the go
towards a set of goals over time you
realize that certain uh you need to
prioritize more some of them so some
maybe less maybe keep some for later
that always works that's how it always
goes so a set of goals is not something
you necessarily have to achieve
completely it's good to have a set of
goals to work to work towards and when
you do that you may end up doing things
that you've not even thought of doing so
that's somehow um that's the kind of
2022 I had I had a set of goals I have a
keep some of those some of those I have
kept for later and I thought I decided
not to finish them in 2022 itself and I
ended up doing several things that I had
not even thought of doing in 2022.
overall 22 was a great year uh very
happy with it and I obviously have a set
of goals for 2023 and I am sure that I
will not achieve all of those but I most
likely will end up achieving something
apart from that as well that's how it
typically goes as long as you work
really hard as long as you're focused
and you have a set of goals so that's
how it was for me and let's take uh the
next question
Ankit says could you please share your
views on the defense deal with Cyprus
what impact would it have from an
international point of view
Alka says what is the significance of
India signing a defense agreement with
Cyprus doing Dr Jai Shankar's visit
recent visit to the country so let's see
what Dr Jay Shankar and other people
have to say about this uh
like a c uh let's take a look at some
tweets by Dr Jay Shankar
um he says great to meet president of
House of Representatives Anita demitriu
interesting conversation on our
parliamentary practices appreciate the
uh presentation of commemorative stamps
marking mahotsav and 60 years of
diplomatic ties and uh some pictures
that go along with that uh so he met uh
who's the president of the House of
Representatives of Cyprus what else does
Mr doctor say
um
apart from that Dr Jason curse says that
uh he also met with a foreign minister
uh yonis casullides in Nicosia which is
the capital of Cyprus the yeah the
Cyprus the third meeting this year but
this one in Cyprus comprehensive
discussions on bilateral ties
cooperation in EU and other multilateral
fora
also exchanged perspectives on our
neighborhood indo-pacific West Asia
and Ukraine yeah
what else uh happened let's take a look
at what the lady has to say this is in
Greek so let's translate that machine
translation in extreme in an extremely
useful discussion with the Indian
Minister of Foreign
ways of
to further deepen bilateral relations
and develop collaborations on critical
issues energy migration and climate
crisis we informed about Turkish
provocations against Cyprus now that's
an interesting perspective so there was
a discussion about uh
Turkish provocations
against
Cyprus
yeah now let's take a look at Cyprus to
understand the the if you don't
understand the geography you won't
understand the the the geopolitics so
let's take a look at the geography of
the region of the country and uh that
obviously informs us a lot so uh we know
where India is let's go westwards
westwards let's go to the Mediterranean
and in the Mediterranean in the East
Mediterranean you have turkey and south
of turkey there's this island called
Cyprus this is a divided island in the
1970s the Turks invaded the island and
captured uh roughly uh the the northern
third or so of the island yeah there is
a line of control as you can see the
dashed lines the southern part is still
Greek historically it's always been
Greek historically even the region of
turkey has been Greek yep so the island
is under uh Turkish occupation right now
yes Nicosia is itself a divided city as
you can see the dashed line passes right
through the heart of Nicosia itself yes
so that's where Dr Jay Shankar went
for on his on his reason to visit Turkey
uh occupies
forcibly the northern roughly one-third
of the island yes
um so the the uh agreements I I believe
three agreements
were signed between India and Cyprus
there was a an agreement on on defense
and Military cooperation more like a
memorandum of agree of understanding
so India and Cyprus will now
cooperate and collaborate from the
defense and Military perspective which
there are no more specifics available as
of today we know this that's there's an
mou that has been signed between India
and Cyprus but the details of the
agreement or the mou uh thus far as as
far as I've seen have not been uh made
specific or made public
so there's gonna be going forward some
kind of defense and Military
collaboration cooperation between India
maybe it could involve some arms sales
Etc from India to Cyprus because India
is a manufacturer manufacturer of of
arms Cyprus is not Greece is not so
there could be
some sales of weapons and weapon systems
in the future arms and all that maybe
there could be visits by Indian naval
ships to Cyprus in the future and and
further we could explore further areas
of cooperation there was also a letter
of intent that for uh about migration
and Mobility that was signed between the
two Nations which essentially will
facilitate the mobility of of students
and business people and professionals
and other people maybe tourists tourists
also uh between India and Cyprus so
Cyprus is a nice location in the
Mediterranean Mediterranean Sea nice
beaches great climate all that yeah so
it's it's a it's a nice place for
Indians to go to maybe for as tourists
and maybe maybe even students if there
are opportunities there so so there's
some kind of agreement that's been
signed about migration and Mobility
between India and Cyprus which will
essentially help the citizens of both
Nations and apart from that there wasn't
there's an agreement that's been signed
uh a framework agreement on the
international solar Alliance which has
been signed by Cyprus
uh this International solar Alliance is
an Indian idea it's been started by
India India is the leader so now Cyprus
has been welcomed in welcomed into the
international solar Alliance so these
are the three main things that have uh
essentially been done signed yeah so
it's it's a good step forward in in
India's relationship with Cyprus and
India's overall Global diplomacy and I
believe the two sides also discussed
various things like the covid-19
pandemic and food security energy
security which again ties in with the
solar Alliance thing and so on so as of
today so what would obviously interest
most of us most people would be the
defense in military agreement that's
been signed whatever is inside but thus
far we don't have the details as and
when details become available if they do
then we will speak about it uh but yeah
effects have not been revealed but it's
a good step overall so we know that
India and turkey don't have the best
relationship India and turkey have never
had the best of best of relationships
right
ever since the partitioning of India by
the British turkey has more or less
consistently taken the side of the
pakistanis yeah and it's mostly been
been kind of to some extent anti-india
not very strongly anti-india and the in
the sense of overt hostilities or
research thing but yes overall their
tone their approach has been more Pro
Pakistan and more empty India
uh so so yeah that's the so in the light
of that fact this is uh a good thing
that India has done so it will put in
some way or the other
some kind of pressure on turkey and this
could be the beginning of that so before
as far as I know India and Cyprus
haven't had much
of any kind of dealings diplomatically
internationally bilaterally Etc so this
is a great step forward and and if India
and Cyprus sign a defense and Military
agreement it the the Cyprus the cypriots
have just one main opponent opponent one
main enemy which is turkey yeah turkey
holds the northern third of the island
and they would like to take out the
whole island eventually if they are
allowed to so if India and Cyprus get
into this relationship it's going to
strengthen Cyprus against the Turks so
essentially this is an anti Turkish move
that's how you could see it and yeah it
serves it works well and obviously India
now is uh
a stronger and the more uh confident
world power and we are seeing all of
this as a consequence of that
so India is projecting its influence
right now it's diplomatically to some
extent militarily also so we also have
to counterbalance what the Turks may be
doing in various parts of the world
their
attitude has always been anti-india so
this is a uh you could say a good
counter to that and uh it's also good
for the cypriots who deserve to be free
of Turkish occupation in their Island
so yeah that's what we know thus far of
this agreement or deal or whatever it is
between India and Cyprus it's not a deal
thus far it's an agreement it's a
memorandum of understanding which opens
up a lot of possibilities for defense
and Military cooperation between the two
nations in the future
yeah
all right khusro says
um can you talk about the major
restoration and why it happened and its
outcomes the lesser-known Greek genocide
part of the broader Assyrian Armenian
and Greek genocide and my thoughts on
the lore of The Lord of the Rings okay
uh look I'll talk about one thing let's
talk about the major restoration I have
uh referred to the major restoration on
on occasion
but uh we've never really discussed in
it in as a separate topic
so I'll just throw some light over on it
I will not obviously give a detailed
Exposition which would take a lot of
time but yeah it's it's a
so Japan is one of the important Nations
if you look at the history of the 19th
and 20th centuries Japan is a major uh
Power major world power Japan
transformed itself into a major world
power military power Imperial power uh
it it suffered uh defeat in the end of
World War II but then it became a U.S uh
occupied territory a U.S vasal state and
it it was allowed to transform itself
into a major uh technological and
economic power until the 1980s it's
still a major technical technological
power but uh economically it's been kind
of ruined so it all kind of kind of
begins with the Meiji restoration so I I
find Japanese history really fascinating
I would encourage all of you to if you
if you are so inclined to read about it
um so okay let's take a look let's put
Japan on them on on the screen yes so
that we all know what we are talking
about so Japan of course we know it's a
small nation but it's had a very uh
significant influence on on global
geopolitics in the past hundred plus
years so what was this niji Reformation
to understand the major Reformation you
do go back in time you can start with
the day the major Reformation starts you
have to go back in time to understand
the context
so the major restoration was essentially
uh something that happened late in the
late 1860s it was
it all begins with a coup a coup d'etat
yeah
it was the overthrow of the feudal
Tokugawa shogunate so the so what was
the Tokugawa shogunate so if you go back
a thousand years before today
um
Japan entered what you could say the era
of the shogunets yeah the Shoguns were
the the uh
see Japanese Society was was divided
into various classes very similar to
Indian Society I mean uh Indian Society
historically was if you look at what
megasthanis said the Greek ambassador to
India two and a half thousand years ago
he said Indian Society was divided into
into seven classes and of late we think
of Indian society as divided into four
classes or caste so whatever you want to
call it that's how the British
you know the nomenclature they imposed
caste system the Japanese had a very
similar thing so you had a
you had the the warrior class you had
the uh the merchant class you had the
agricultural class and so on yep and you
also had the administrators and and
officials and all that and the that's
the kind of society Japan had
essentially a four-fold division of
society
so uh
so about a thousand years ago the
samurai the Warriors became very
dominant in Japanese society and uh they
uh established what you could call it it
happened this way that the sugar net
system was established the Shogun was
the the it was the greatest power one
person who is at the head of the entire
nation it is not the emperor the emperor
was just a nominal Emperor for all this
time yeah the emperor was essentially a
figurehead but the real power lay within
the hands of the Shogun who was the
ruler of the Samurai and in the entire
nation more or less so technically they
were under the emperor but actually they
were the real power the Shoguns so uh
so Japan was under the system for a
beginning about a thousand or so years
ago obviously if you go back in time
there's a whole different story in Japan
there's a significant influence of
Indian culture in Japan which which
syncretized itself with the indigenous
Shinto Traditions so
the Indian culture that came into Japan
came via China and it's mostly what
you've got what you what you would call
Buddhist culture but obviously it is not
just about this culture you had all the
various Hindu divinities in this yeah
um so
um and Shinto is more like Japanese
Hinduism it's it's it's it
emerged and evolved completely
independently in Japan but it's
extremely similar to Japan to Hinduism
there is more there are more
similarities between Shinto and Hinduism
than between Hinduism and and it's
offshore to Buddhism anyhow that's a
different story beginning a thousand
years ago we have the shogunate system
more or less in Japan about half a
millennium ago you had the beginning of
the European Travelers starting to go
across the world in their ships they had
acquired this new technology from
wherever they acquired we know where
they acquired from and so on so they
began they began the Europeans begin uh
circumnavigating the world and trying to
find out what lies in different parts of
the world and in the uh 18th and 19th
century they began to uh establish their
dominance
in Asia we know what what the Europeans
uh did to India we don't need to repeat
that they also overran China to some
extent we had the Opium Wars and all
that
and
with the beginning of the European
influence in this region the the
Tokugawa shogunate essentially closed
off the nation
the nature of Japan to outside forces so
Japan was essentially a incomplete ISO
they adopted the policy of isolating
Japan from external influences so they
would they refused to allow European
ships to to dock in Japanese Port the
Tokugawa shogunate
um they had seen the influence that
Christianity brought into Japan they
observed that Japanese citizens who
became Christians turned anti-national
that's what they observed that's what
they write okay it's not my opinion
that's what they've written so they
banned the entry of Europeans into into
Japan if you look if you read European
histories of Japan of this era they will
say there was large-scale persecution of
Christians yeah that's what they claim
and so on
so for a couple of hundred years for
about two centuries Japan was isolated
Japan adopted a policy of isolation
isolationism from the world
then in the 19th century the Americans
started coming to Japan and they refused
to go away when they were ordered by the
Tokugawa shogunate they came in big
ships with powerful guns cannons and all
that and when the Tokugawa forces would
tell them to go away they would refuse
and they would come and Dock and they
would and and I don't know what was the
name of the American Admiral some Perry
William Perry or some Perry or something
he said that I would I will come back in
one year and I and you better give me a
positive response otherwise we will we
can you know we will we will not accept
your policy of isolationism we want to
trade with Japan and Japan had resources
like coal are the things that the
Americans wanted the Europeans wanted
so the Europeans wanted to trade with
Japan and um so
the Tokugawa policy of isolationism was
not going to work forever and that's why
in the 1860s 1867 68 or so there was an
overthrow
of the Tokugawa shogunate it was a coup
d'etat and it was a bunch of people who
did that um and they propped up the
Meiji Emperor who was a teenager a young
boy as the as the emperor of Japan and
the Tokugawa shogunate was overthrown
this is a coup d'etat and obviously it
was not an easy process there were
rebellions for some time the certain
sections of the Samurai cooperated then
they realized that Samurai are being
essentially wiped out of existence all
their uh Power all their privileges are
going to disappear so there were
rebellions yeah so this goes on for
about about about two decades two three
decades almost yeah the rebellions and
all that
um and the real power lay not with the
Meiji Emperor but with his cabinet
that's where the real power lay the
Meiji Emperor was essentially a
figurehead uh so even during the
shogunate era the emperor was a
figurehead even during the major
restoration era the emperor was more or
less a figurehead the real power lay
with the cabinet so then the shogunate
was overthrown the samurai rebelled
there were two or three rebellions of
the of the Samurai these were eventually
crushed and a new kind of Japan was
created a constitutional uh Imperial
State uh and uh the emphasis was on a
on importing Western a western Outlook
Western technology yeah but keeping some
kind of balance and and preserving
Japanese culture to some extent yeah uh
and there was an attempt to Stamp Out
Buddhism from Japan which failed but
even today as a consequence of that the
Japanese people now see Buddhism as an
external religion it's something that
came in from outside before that it was
not seen that way
so they attempted to Stamp Out Buddhism
that failed but they brought in a very
different Outlook they they essentially
the samurai were crushed and they no
longer have any influence in Japanese
Society since then uh and they adopted a
very Western
mindset and
it from this point onwards Japan becomes
uh an imperial power so they're very
rapidly modernized they're very rapidly
industrialized they adopted Universal
education which may not have been there
before that they uh they adopted a
system of conscription and a standing
army which became a very powerful Army
yeah
um and the Japanese in order to uh to
get the to gain respect in the eyes of
the West started a policy of imperialism
and colonialism so they essentially
started uh colonizing parts of
Eastern China the manchuoko region what
is now China which historically has not
been China so the region east of Japan
they colonized parts of Korea eventually
all of Korea yeah occupied that they
occupied manchuoku as well present-day
Manchuria
and they came into conflict with the
Chinese and even with the Russians so
that's a whole story but uh so so that's
what happened
that's what the Meiji restoration was
about it was a coup d'etat which over
through the old feudal system the
samurai system the shogunate era the
Tokugawa shogunate it brought in a huge
wave of complete uh modernization of
Japan and westernization of Japan the
Army this during the samurai
the the warriors were very deeply
uh in culturated they were they had this
system called Bushido which is the the
samurai code of honor they were very
honorable people they were very clear
sense of Ethics what could be done what
could not be done
the samurai where where for the longest
time eating meat was prohibited in Japan
in in Slaughter of cattle was prohibited
in Japan the samurai were great warriors
but they were mostly vegetarians you
know that's a strange thing
um so all of that was thrown out of out
of the window
and the new Army that came into power
was a very different force it was a very
westernized Force the the uh influence
of culture of dharmic culture of Shinto
culture all of that was taken out yeah
and the Army was essentially a western
style modern professional Army which
followed the orders of the of the
superiors unquestioningly yeah and that
is something that led to the the
horrific atrocities that uh Japan later
on went on to perpetrate
uh during its its uh era of expansionism
Imperial expansionism and colonialism
yeah
um so that is essentially what the uh
major restoration was and the outcome so
it transformed Japan in within a couple
of decades into an expansionist
colonialist imperialist power that
brought Japan
respect in the eyes of the voice they
said the westerners said that oh my
goodness look at that Japan is behaving
like a Civilized Nation just like us
uh so maybe that's that's the kind of
thing the the that they wanted you know
uh so yeah so that's kind of what
happened that was the what the major
restoration was about and its outcomes I
will not discuss the other things
because that will take too much time but
it's uh yeah so that's what the major
restoration was about and it totally
transformed Japan eventually led to the
defeat of Japan in World War II and uh
various other things as well and what
you see in Japan today is essentially a
direct outcome of a process that was set
in Motion in the 1860s and 1870s the
Meiji restoration
rudrajit says tensions between Russia
and Japan are increasing day by day over
the kuril islands the kuril islands as
Russia and Japan both are very important
for India's geopolitical economical and
Military interests according to you what
should be India's stance on this issue
interesting question
um so let's talk about the coral island
dispute yeah
um
that's a dispute that's been simmering
for about I don't know 80 years 80
almost 80 years let's talk about that so
I spoke about the Meiji restoration just
a second ago yeah
so during the Meiji major era even
during the Tokugawa shogunate era
Japan had started expanding in various
directions yeah
and one of the uh directions it expanded
was it was in the North
so Japan
had
I believe the this island
the island of sakhalin which is now a
Russian Island
was once a Japanese island at least
that's the the southern half of the
island was under Japanese control and
all of the kiral islands in the 19th
century were under Japanese control the
curled islands are this chain of islands
all right
this here in the middle of the screen is
the northernmost Japanese main island of
Hokkaido
and north of the island of Hokkaido we
have this island here sakhalin Island
and over here we have the various Coral
Islands as you can see it's written here
Coral islands and this goes on all the
way up to here until the Kamchatka
Peninsula which is a Russian Peninsula
now
um in the 19th century the Japanese and
the Russians had various agreements at
one point in time uh Japan and Russia
had decided to share control over the
sakhali island the northern half would
be Russian the southern half would be
Japanese yep the the Russians too had a
policy of expansionism yeah Russia
obviously as we know the capital is has
been Moscow but uh they expanded
eastwards they also had this policy of
settler colonialism and this entire
Eurasian landmass that is currently part
of Russia was all conquered by the
Russians the peoples who live here are
not Russian people they are there
essentially uh
don't go sick people two one people
Siberian people people who have uh
turkic ethnicity uh mongolic ethnicity
and and so on yeah in the north you have
the ainu people who live in this region
especially in the who have historically
lived in the coral Islands so
in the middle of the eighth 19th century
the Russians and Japanese shared
sakhalin Island and uh there was an
agreement which uh said that Japan could
uh essentially
take control of all the coral Islands up
to the tip of the Kamchatka Peninsula
yeah so this situation
stood for a very long time
and then the Russians expanded eastwards
they took over Manchuria and they they
also took uh control of the uh Port City
of Dalian which is currently part of
China and they established a major port
of Vladivostok which is right north of
North Korea all right now during the
second world war Japan as we know fought
the United States and the Western allies
and eventually in 1945
Japan was defeated
Japan Was Defeated Japan was made to
surrender after the twin Atomic tests on
Hiroshima and Nagasaki yes so a couple
of days after the atomic test on on
Hiroshima the Soviets so the Soviets
and the Japanese had a non-aggression or
some kind of agreement which was due to
expire in 1946 in 1946 but at the end of
the war just before Japan surrenders in
1945 itself these Soviets launched an
invasion of the crude Island just the
crude island chain just two days after
the atomic test on Hiroshima the
American Atomic test or Hiroshima
so the the Japanese were reeling from
This Disaster and a couple of days just
a few days later there was another test
on Nagasaki
and a week after Hiroshima the Japanese
had to surrender
while this was happening the Soviets
they broke the non-aggression pact that
whatever treaty they had and illegally
invaded the cruel Islands
and the kuril islands the the
inhabitants were all Japanese so the
Russia the Soviets very rapidly came all
the way South up to
up to these islands what is this island
called kunashir what is this one called
it's called zelioni this one is called
shikothan and so on so all these islands
were taken
were captured
forcibly by the Soviets and they
expelled all the Japanese inhabitants
and and relocated them forcibly to the
Japanese mainland
and uh then the the Soviets settled
Slavic
peoples in these islands in sakhalin in
the kurul islands mainly Russian and
Ukrainian speakers yeah
um so one could argue that the Soviet
invasion of the kiril islands was
illegal because they had this pact
that's non-aggression or whatever pact
it was a peace back to peace treaty or
whatever it was it was which was
supposed to last until 1946.
so the Japanese had been they were
defeated the Soviets invaded these
islands Etc then the Americans imposed
certain treaties on the Japanese the
Japanese were forced to sign these
treaties one of these treaties says that
the Japanese will relinquish all all
claims on the kuril islands yeah that's
one of the treaties and various other
things as well
as a consequence of all of these things
that happened the Japanese have always
claimed that the cruel islands of the
the four kiril Islands up to uh I
believe the island of Europe I if not
this one then up to the island of
ithurope
so they claim four cruel islands and
they said that these islands have been
captured illegally by the Soviet Union
and now Russia is the is the
continuation of the Soviet Union
and as a consequence of that Japan and
Russia Japan and the USSR never signed
a ceasefire which means that technically
World War II is still not over because
the ceasefire between Japan and the USSR
was never signed and the ceasefire
between Japan and Russia has also never
been signed so the Russians Soviets and
now Russians they they have typically
offered Japan control of two islands two
small Islands they said that we will
offer you these two islands and in
exchange you need to relinquish your
claims on all the other islands and the
Japanese have steadfastly refused
that's the situation in the crude
Islands now why is it
that these islands are so important why
is Russia
hanging on to these islands which seem
to be small and unimportant it's the
same kind of question I get from some
very I mean some people that what's the
big deal about nehru relinquishing
what's the big deal it's just a small
piece of territory where nothing grows
that's the kind of silly
uh argument some people make so
understand that every inch of territory
has strategic value and I'll show you
why
so the Russians the Soviet Union and
today Russia see earlier so we didn't
the Soviet Soviets had uh the Russians
had access to Dalian Port Dalian is kind
of for the South which means that it
doesn't freeze in the winter if you see
Vladivostok the port of Vladivostok
which is the southernmost port in this
video that the Russians have it freezes
in Winter for for at least two or three
months I don't remember how much more
how much but it freezes totally it's
it's it's ice Bound in winter so the so
the Russian uh Pacific Fleet
uh it is it is based in the vicinity of
lady vostok yeah
so it for the Russian Pacific Fleet to
navigate the oceans it uh in in winter
it's quite difficult and uh for this
Pacific Fleet Russian Pacific Fleet to
to go into the high seas of the Pacific
Ocean it has to go through several choke
points there are let me show you what
choke points exist
you have the island of of tsushima here
so there is this straight the Korean
straight to the west of tujima there is
a different state straight to the right
to the to the east of tsushima there is
a small straight over here
or between these islands in Japan
these so South Korea is militarily
occupied by the U.S
Japan is under permanent military
occupation tens of thousands of U.S
troops in both the Nations
so these Straits are under constant
surveillance by the Americans so
anything that happens here the Americans
will know immediately so if the Soviet
or later Russian Fleet were to try to go
into the Pacific Ocean from here the
Americans will know exactly what's
happening and that's not an ideal
situation the other straight straight
choke point is here
between Hokkaido and and the the main
island of Japan that also is obviously
under constant U.S uh supervision the
other straight is between sakhalin and
Hokkaido which is kind of you know
something that the Russians can use and
then you have the kuril islands now if
the kuril islands were to go back into
Japanese uh control it means the the
Americans will immediately establish a
military bases there and then they will
be able to to uh monitor everything that
the Russians are doing now if you go to
the northern Coral Islands these are
very strongly ice Bound in Winter even
the southern curable islands are
icebound but the northern irelands are
house ice Bound for at least two months
more so that's why the coral islands are
strategically very important if the
Americans take if the Japanese which
means the Americans take control of the
silence then the entire so Russian
Pacific Fleet will be totally uh hemmed
in it's like the island China the the
Island the island chains that the
Chinese are so upset about these Island
chains ring offense the Chinese Navy and
the Americans are able to monitor
everything the Chinese do as a
consequence yeah so that's why the coral
islands are so strategically important
for the Russians of course there's also
the the question of oil and gas if you
see sakhalin uh the northern North East
part of sakhalin offshore has very
significant reserves of oil and natural
gas yeah very very major results of oil
and natural gas it's possible that the
curled Islands Also may have significant
reserves of oil and natural gas so why
should the Russians give that up so that
is the dispute that's what the dispute
is all about and after the so after the
Russian invasion of Ukraine the Japanese
have been upping the antique and making
these noises that cruel islands is a
dispute territory and we want it back
obviously at the instigation of the US
and I would say that you know
it if you look at the way history is
unfolded one could say that Japan that
Japan has a very strong claim and a
rightful claim on the cruel Islands but
but Justice there is no such thing as
Justice yeah in in geopolitics whoever
holds the islands is the rightful owner
that's how it goes might is right so the
Russians have a significant uh military
a significant military presence on these
islands yeah they have anti-aircraft
batteries they have they have missiles
that are installed over here missile
systems uh troops as well over here and
there is a significant Russian and
Ukrainian speaking population that has
been settled in these islands so the
Russians are not going anywhere they are
not going to give up the claim then
they're not going to give up the islands
and there's not much the Japanese can do
right now as long as the Russians have
the military strength and the
capabilities to hold on to these islands
and these are very vital and
strategically important islands for
Russia so why would they give it up
now the question so that's the curiel
islands dispute now Russia and Japan
both are important to India in various
ways what should India's stance be on
the issue India's stance should be it's
not our concern it's not our business
both Nations should find a peaceful
resolution to the to the debate to the
to the issue
you need to India India would say that
Japan and Russia should sit down and
negotiate it and find a diplomatically
negotiated solution to the disputed uh
Island accurate Islands issue no war
please don't go to war this is not an
era for war that's what we say so that
should be India's stance on this issue
Japan essentially is an extension of the
US I it really it's very unfortunate
that the wonderful people of Japan are
under uh foreign military occupation for
the past almost eight years it's
terrible for them yeah uh but yeah Japan
as of today is an extension of the US
it's a U.S visal state it's under total
almost total permanent U.S military
occupation
um
so yes Japan obviously has
significant importance for India
culturally we have the very old
relationship between India and Japan and
um so culturally we are very much alike
of course Japan now doesn't have an
independent foreign or military policy
so whatever they do is essentially what
the Americans tell them to do so that's
how it is so India should stay out of
these uh these disputes it's not India's
business we should exhort both sides to
refrain from any warmongering any
violence and both sides need to sit down
at the negotiating table
and find a negotiated settlement or
solution to this uh to this dispute that
should be India's official position on
the matter
says uh you always said Germany Japan
and to some extent Italy are under
permanent U.S military occupation then
why don't we see Germany or Japan's
footballers or other renowned figures
showing recentment about their country's
occupation by a foreign power why is it
so you know there is this uh
very famous Korean rapper called Psy the
guy who sang Gangnam Style
it emerged after so he released this
song called Gangnam Style it's become a
phenomenon maybe the most viewed video
on YouTube billions plus views and all
that he became a global phenomenon and
then it emerged that about 15 or so I
don't know a decade or so ago he had
made anti-us statements on the record
his South Korean
and he was made to publicly apologize
for this and and express regret for what
he had said yeah so it's not like people
don't know uh the the current chancellor
of Germany Mr Olaf Schultz as a student
had participated in anti-us protests
but today he's a good boy and that's why
he has been appointed he is he has
changed his opinion he is now reformed
and he he now has been allowed to ascend
to the top position in Germany which
only happens with the with the ascent of
the Imperial Overlord which is the
United States so it's not like no one
knows about this but you cannot make too
much of a noise about this if you know
what is best for you in these nations
um and mostly what happens like about a
year or so ago I spoke about arminius
Army news uh was a German freedom
fighter that time there was no Germany
there were the various um Germanic
tribes or Clans that lived in in what is
now Germany and they were under the
Roman yoke under Roman occupation this
guy arminius was the son of a of the
chieftain of the cherouski or some tribe
yes and he was taken hostage by the
Romans and he was brought up as a Roman
Prince as a Roman as part of the new
Roman nobility so it was assumed by the
Romans that he would be loyal to the to
the to Rome so he uh
was given charge of a major he became he
he rose in the military ranks and then
he was uh defeated to Germany as part of
the Roman occupying forces he switched
sides and he defected to his people
he raised uh he kind of unified certain
coalitions he created a unified
Coalition of various Germanic tribes he
taught them the Roman way of warfare he
understood how the Roman War Machine
worked and in the Battle of tutorberg
forest which is which happened I think
in in nine or eight A.D in the Battle of
tutor book Forest the Germans under
arminius were able to annihilate three
Roman Legions and this set of a a chain
of events that within two centuries
would end in the uh
in the decline and destruction of the
Western Roman Empire yeah it took a
couple of centuries but after this event
things started changing gradually so
arminius who is
the first great German Freedom Fighter
we could say he fought against Imperial
occupation
and this he should be a major figure in
Germany but in in the year 2009 or
whatever it was or 2012 I don't remember
which area you can look it up that was
the 2000th anniversary of the battle of
tutorberg forest in which the Germans
defeated the Romans and yet almost
nobody celebrated this in Germany why
because this is not this was not taught
at the time in Germany's history
textbooks so if you are taught lies you
will not know what's happening you will
not know what's happening yeah Germany's
Constitution has been written under the
U.S under U.S supervision I'm not sure
how many Germans know this it all
depends on what you're taught whatever
you're taught as a kid you you hold on
to that emotionally
and in the film and later if somebody
tells you something else you will you
will react emotionally and say you're
wrong you're telling lies
for the longest time in India
children were taught that the mughals
the turkic occupiers of India the brutal
barbarians who bled India for 700 years
we were taught
that these mughals were were the
greatest saviors of India and they were
they were good for India
Akbar was great and so on even today if
you tell a kid or a young person that
Akbar was actually a brutal killer then
they will they will you know accuse you
of trying to rewrite history and all
that
so it doesn't matter what's happening as
long as the overall narrative by is is
that your nation is free and all that
then people will not know about it
all you have to do is is to have a
certain kind of of narrative that is
propagated through the education system
and the same narrative should also be
reinforced by the leaders of the nation
and by the media in the media in Japan
is controlled in South Korea and Germany
is controlled by pro-western forces and
the leaders are Western puppets so what
do you expect yeah even in Pakistan
I I know for a fact that in Pakistani
textbooks
glorify and eulogize
uh brutal barbarians like gory and
gaznavi yeah who did so much harm to the
ancestors of the Pakistani people
and yet today's pakistanis considered
them to be like next to God yeah
so that's how it is that's how it goes
the power of power of propaganda the
power of misleading people and
distorting history through the education
system through the media and through
your leaders that's how it goes so
that's why you don't see any of this
happening some people know about it but
they are
suppressed and marginalized that's how
it goes
unfortunate
uh Daniel Nicholson says could you
please enlighten us about the secret new
secret nuclear City
in chitradurga District why was the West
so alarmed by its construction in the
not so distant past interesting uh
question you ask yes interesting
question let's take a look let me put
that on the screen what is the whole
deal about the secret uh nuclear City
so this is an article
uh from a which year is this this is
December 16 2015 right this is about
seven years ago seven whatever it is six
seven eight years six seven years ago
India is building a top secret nuclear
City to produce thermonuclear weapons
experts say these weapons could upgrade
India as a nuclear power and deeply
unsettled Pakistan and China so what's
your problem foreign policy
it's a U.S publication yeah uh
so that's a whole long story about this
yeah and uh
they they speak about various Indians
who are against this you know local
villagers who have been evicted
apparently from their from their lands
and all that uh it also kind of reveals
certain Indian insiders who are working
against the interests of India who are
working against in the Indian government
let me show you an example
there is this person called Leo Saldana
founding member of some advocacy
organization who writes about uh how you
know
how tribal communities and local farming
communities are being walled off and so
on these are all lies there are lots of
aspiring zelinski's within India who are
very happy to help foreign forces
undermine India's national interests
yeah
so in this article this place is being
portrayed as a future uh nuclear City a
top secret nuclear City to produce
thermonuclear weapons right so that's
what the West was apparently so alarmed
about they don't want India to make any
progress obviously we know that so what
exactly is going on in challakere let's
take a look yeah because you see
yeah okay let me put that on the screen
so first of all please understand I am
showing you information that's available
in the public domain I'm not showing you
any secret or sensitive information
anybody
who has access to the internet can see
this okay so I'm not showing you
anything uh any any any classified
information
let's take a look at falakere where is
it
so let's uh locate this on the map it's
in Karnataka in in Peninsula or India in
Southern India yes so let's go to uh the
the town the region of shalak and what's
what's going on here let's uh put the
satellite view on the screen and very
soon you will know what's happening here
so north west of chalakere we have the
chitra Durga aeronautical test range
zoom into it you will see that uh
there's this place as you can see
there's a Runway and there are some drdo
facilities over here yeah
um so that's what it is so this was not
a secret nuclear City this was they were
building an aeronautical test range and
this is information that anybody can see
so I'm not showing anything classified
or secret or sensitive all right this is
all out in the open
Let's uh just briefly take a look at the
disc how long this Runway is from tip to
tip it's about 2.87 kilometers long so
it's a it's a reasonably
a long Runway and there's a shorter
I don't know it's no that's just one
Runway over here so essentially this is
a place where you can where the drdo ETC
the Indian government and the drdo they
most likely would be testing uh
experimental aircraft and so on I
believe the drdo gothic was tested over
here possibly if I am not mistaken yeah
so this is this is uh where India tests
this is one of the places where India
tests uh
aircraft that are under development
that's what it is it's not a secret
nuclear city as was being alleged by the
west and uh why was the West so alarm
because they don't want India to make
any progress of any kind they want India
to remain a mediocre middling
unambitious zero future uh third world
nation they don't want India to become a
major world power but unfortunately it's
not working for them yeah so that's what
the uh
secret nucleicity or whatever was about
it was not a nuclear City it was it's
already become an aeronautical test
range that's what it is
ah someone says what would be
tajikistan's role in case of India China
war considering the fact that India has
air bases in Tajikistan China also has a
dispute with Tajikistan yes China also
has a dispute with Tajikistan that's
once again go to the map to understand
what is
happening give me a second
all right let's put that on the map once
again where's the map where's the map
here's the map
all right
so in case some of you may not be aware
in case one second let me do this again
yes here we are
the map so in case some of you are not
aware Tajikistan is almost India's
neighboring country
yeah as you can see so
some of this territory is currently
temporarily illegally occupied by
Pakistan Pakistan Kashmir
um
but right across the wahan corridor of
Afghanistan we have the nation of
Tajikistan which is very close to India
very it is adjacent to Afghanistan and
very close to Pakistan now what air
bases are we referring to there are two
one is aini
Air Base
let's see where it is zoom in boom there
we are so let's see let's Orient
ourselves as you can see it is in the
western part of Tajikistan if you can
see it yeah as you can see India is over
here not not far away uh Afghanistan
Kabul is not far and Pakistan is not far
so let's now zoom in and see what kind
of uh information we can see visually
see the satellite view there we are so
this is a reasonably long and
significant reasonably respectable Air
Base let's see the length of the runway
tip to tip
uh oh wow 3.23 kilometers that is
extensive yeah and if we zoom in once
again I'm not showing anything that is
secret this is all open source
information anybody can see this
so there are various installations you
can see a whole bunch of helicopters
these look like these look like Russian
made mil helicopters there are Attack
Helicopters also apparently yeah we're
not sure which one what model it is
uh yeah interesting helicopters this
looks like an Indian dhruva helicopter
if I am not mistaken yeah and there are
these aircraft over here these look like
sukhois of some kind these clearly are
swing Wing aircraft uh so this is the
air base one of the air bases we're
talking about it is jointly operated by
Indian Tajikistan which is the other Air
Base Let's uh this the other one is
called far core
parkour Airbase let's see where that is
so once again let's Orient ourselves
first by zooming out
so this is closer to the Afghan border
and closer to Pakistan now let's zoom in
and see what far core Air Base looks
like
so this doesn't look like much we don't
see a proper
Runway
I don't know from when this image was
taken and you don't see any aircraft
either anyhow this Airbase is also said
to be jointly operated by India and
Tajikistan
now let's go back to any all right one
second and see the distance
in earbuds and we'll zoom out so I want
to say the distance between any airbase
and let's say
and let us say Rawalpindi where is our
Rawalpindi
so let's take a bird's eye distance
measure distance
it's about 680 kilometers a straight
line now we know it is it is said that
at any air base we have certain we have
a number of Indian Sukhoi 30 mki fighter
planes and various other assets of hours
aerial assets Air Force assets so
these two air bases for core and I need
are not aimed at China
the intention is to uh
the the objective is not China it is
Pakistan
these straight line distance from I need
to Rob India is 680 kilometers the
Sukhoi 30 uh has a capability of Mach 2
speed twice the speed of sound but let's
say it's it's cruising at Mach 1.5 let's
say yeah
um if you
if you if you calculate that's that
that's about 23 kilometers per minute
So within a matter of minutes the
sukhoes could be close to Rawalpindi and
actually the sukhoids don't even need to
be over Pakistani territory they just
need to overfly Afghanistan and launch
missiles if need be
so the Indian uh air bases in Tajikistan
are not aimed at China they are aimed at
Pakistan and like you say Tajikistan has
not Tajikistan China has a border
dispute with Tajikistan and Google
obviously always shows this it shows a
dashed line which kind of confirms
China's claims on tajikistani territory
Google somehow is very is very
accommodative of Chinese perceptions
even though Google is banned in China
very surprising don't you see I'm just
saying
um
so the question is what would be
tajikistan's role in India China war
considering that India has air bases in
Tajikistan tajikistan's role in a
potential future India China war would
be that of this is not my concern this
is not my problem this is not my
business it's not my responsibility
Tajikistan will want to stay out of this
yeah because China is right next door to
Tajikistan and they don't want to feel
the Chinese wrath they this entire
situation of the two Indian air bases in
Tajikistan is entirely aimed at Pakistan
yeah in a matter of minutes India can
send Air Force assets close to Pakistan
or if required deep within Pakistani
territory so that's what it is about
there are no major Chinese Targets near
Tajikistan I mean
Etc are not major military installations
the in military installations that we
are interested in with respect to China
are the ones in Tibet
and so on yeah the Chinese have a
military
assets and installations in Tibet close
to India the India table in in Nepal
Tibet borders these are the ones that
concern us these are very far away from
the Indian Air Force bases in Tajikistan
so the Tajikistan air bases are
entirely focused on Pakistan that's what
it is
okay Coastal says in your Indian
interest video you said that from the
Ukraine conflict India should learn and
focus more on drone technology and
missile systems we also we should focus
on cyber warfare but we are still
waiting to induct even one indigenous
drone meanwhile turkey and Iran are
drone export leaders what can we learn
to learn from these two Nations
excellent question
so yeah let's not go back into the
lessons of the Ukraine war I said that
we need to focus on on drone technology
now you don't develop drone technology
over a matter of of six months or two
years takes some time for these
Technologies to to iteratively mature
you have to start from scratch
essentially yeah and then you slowly
build on whatever you've learned and you
make better and better drones there are
several generations of drones look at
the generations of Indian missiles we
started with a very very basic and very
primitive rudimentary one missile which
is a liquid fuel missile now it is being
replaced by the by the
yeah so
India started uh deploying indigenous
missiles in the early 1990s now we're in
the 2020s the missiles that we are now
deploying are incredibly sophisticated
compared to those primitive missiles
that we had it took 30 40 years for the
missile program in technology in India
to really mature and become very
sophisticated India has a very
sophisticated missile ballistic missile
and other missile program today
ballistic missiles cruise missiles and
all and and there are certain missiles
that we don't we may not even be aware
of here so it took about 40 years for
the program to become really cutting
edge and very sophisticated the same
goes for India space program we started
with very uh rudimentary Rockets now we
have some of the best rocket technology
in the world yes
so when it comes to drones let's talk
about turkey right you you referring to
Turkey we also refer to Iran let's take
the example of turkey yeah so the Turks
are now one of the leaders in drone
technology so
so they have this company called biker
which manufactures a bunch of drones by
car is a private Turkish Defense
technology now once again statutory
warning Wikipedia is not always reliable
I'm just using it for convenience
uh especially when it comes to history
it's not reliable so uh this company was
founded by car in 18 in 1984 is by car
makina yeah by osdemeer by rakhtar it
was founded in 1984. in and so it's been
around for a long long time and they
they have a strong uh foundation and
background in in uh Precision machinery
and all these things automatic
constructing automate Automotive Parts
engines pumps and spare parts so they
have a very strong understanding of
foundation in this mechanical
engineering now in the early 2000s
the son of of Osama by rakhtar seljuk he
was studying in MIT I believe yeah
no he was in
the completed his Masters in MIT Etc uh
so he returned to Turkey in 2007 cutting
his PhD studies short short and he
started developing drone technology so
the company already had a very strong
foundation in mechanical engineering and
all these things and this guy came back
in 2007 to work with his daddy with his
father
and within five years they started
developing very uh uh capable drones
then his brother younger brother all I
don't know his brother haluk also joined
the company and
so essentially the company had a very
strong foundation in mechanical
engineering from 2007 onwards they
started focusing on drones and today in
2023 they have some of the best drones
in the world let's take a look at some
of the drones that they have uh let's
put that on the screen
so it takes time to mature you
iteratively mature this so they have a
by rakhtar mini UAV the tb1 the TV2 the
akingchi the TV3 and the Kizi lilma uh
so that's the the Drone family that they
have let's take a look at the tb2 which
is one of the more sophisticated roles
that they have it's being used in
Ukraine and other places yes
so this then this took them a lot of
time to develop this kind of drone yeah
so that is the tb2 which is one of the
best drones they have and now they are
developing the Red Apple the Kizi lilma
so the kissilelma uh we don't see images
of that right now let's try to Google
some images of the Kizi lilma this is a
drone that is still under development
this has it incorporates some elements
of stealth technology you can see from
the shape that it it is uh stealth
capable to a certain extent so it's
taken them
decades to reach this position it's not
something you can do in two two years
three years five years yeah it takes
time you need a strong Foundation of uh
of technology to be able to do this even
the Chinese have a whole lot of drones
they've been developing for the third
past 30 40 50 years they have been
testing all kinds of drones for for
decades India has only now started
focusing on drone technology it takes
time
for this to develop and mature we need
to pour in substantial funds into this
and it's it's wrong to have I mean it's
it's fine see in Turkey there's just one
one company that's doing this in China
there are a lot of uh different
institutes that are working on drone
technology
we need to have funds and we need to
have the right Minds you have to attract
the right minds and then build on
whatever you've learned so it takes time
I would say it would take India about
five to ten years to develop a stealth
capable drone we already are developing
a stealth drone uh flying wing drone
called the drdo ghatak it was earlier
called the aura we have certain other
projects under development I think that
India can a accelerate the production of
these Technologies
we have drdo we have
various
see drdo is a very bureaucratic
organization it's it's not a private
company uh by car is a private company
it's it's run specifically
for a certain purpose drdo is a very
very sprawling organization we certainly
need to reform the way these
organizations are run cut down on all
the extraneous stuff drdo is a staff of
how much 30 000 out of which only five
thousand are scientists so what are 25
000 non-scientists doing in drdo it's a
huge drain of money so we need to for we
need to do something about this we need
to reform these organizations maybe
bring in the private sector I think the
brains the talent the capability the
know-how it's all there in India we need
to find ways of leveraging that
um
so either the government should should
uh give out contracts to private uh
and and we know that India is now
becoming a drone Hub you know private
companies are manufacturing drones not
necessarily military drones but the
know-how they acquire in manufacturing
commercial drones and developing the
technology will definitely have military
applications so we are now building the
capability to
to do these things I think within a
decade India could very surprisingly
become a nation at the Forefront of some
of these Technologies so what we can
learn from Nations that have done well
in designing and developing drone
technology is that we have to invest
in this technology for a long period of
time we have to attract the best Minds
we have to provide sufficient funds and
we have to understand that there are
several generations of technology which
are built on top of the previous
generations so uh that's the thing so I
think now now India is going in the
right direction obviously we can still
do better we can still do much better
but we are in the on the right track now
I think within a decade India could be
one of the major drone manufacturing
Nations not just commercial drones but
actually military drones as well yeah
Daniel says how long will it take for
the Indian military industrial complex
to mature what other products and
services could India export and Achieve
absolute Monopoly on so as to become a
civilizational giant well military
military technology has nothing to do
with being um
well yeah of course it all goes hands
hand in hand you cannot become a strong
civilization without having a powerful
military industrial complex which
which of course lends itself to you
becoming an imperial power as well but
yeah so how long will it take for the
Indian military industrial complex to
mature well when it comes to certain
sectors it's already very greatly mature
when it comes to Rocket technology in as
an ISRO it's definitely matured it's
been there for a long time I think India
has the capability within the next five
years to develop a
uh um
the kind of uh Rockets the the SpaceX
has SpaceX I think the first rocket
flight was in 2006 or 2007 if I'm not
mistaken and in just 15 or so years
they've become you know they are
launching Rockets almost every week and
they have already developed one of the
most powerful Rockets the world has ever
seen in the Falcon whatever it is yeah
the mothership or whatever I think India
has the ability and the know-how in ISRO
to within the next
five years to develop rocket of the
caliber we have it we just don't we just
lack the funding we just lack the
political will for that
uh so when it comes to ISRO and space
technology rocket technology I think we
are already at a very mature phase when
it comes to missile technology we are
already extremely mature when it comes
to aircraft fighter aircraft technology
we are intermediate an intermediate step
we have now developed a fully
world-class light combat aircraft we
still don't have as far as we know the
um
the jet engine technology as far as we
know uh so now we are at an intermediate
step stage once we have the uh
the tejus Mark II and the amca which
would which would take a decade then we
will be at a more mature phase so I
think India is about a decade away from
becoming a sophisticated mature aircraft
manufacturer when it comes to other
Technologies like submarines and all I
think we already have production lines
that we can leverage certain things we
have to learn on on our own so I would
say that instead of buying we already
have developed a nuclear submarine Forum
a whole class of nuclear submarines we
are able to uh build aircraft carriers
on our own so in various domains we have
various differing degrees of maturity I
think within a decade or so India could
be a very mature uh could have a very
mature military industrial complex there
are certain things India can manufacture
on its own like how it serves and
whatnot
um so yeah we need to bring in the
private companies into the private
sector into this there is so much uh
capacity available in the private sector
so that's something that needs to be
leveraged I think within a decade we
could have a very mature military
industrial complex and we could become a
major exporter of these things you know
we are already exporting um weapons to
Azerbaijan we may be exporting the the
brahmos missile to various Nations
various Nations that are interested we
will we're already exporting helicopters
to various Nations we uh even the lc8
Ages was in contention in various places
but certain strings were pulled at some
places in other
South Korean
light combat aircraft one at the end of
the day this is more political than
actually based on your capabilities
so India needs to first start
manufacturing all of its own weapons for
its own purposes once you can do that
you can start exporting things so I
think we are about a decade or so away
so I'm very optimistic about this
right
how can I learn Sanskrit if I can't read
or write Hindi I learn in I live in
Australia never needed to learn Hindi
and what makes Sanskrit such an
excellent programming language why is it
so similar to Greek and Latin and how
did people thousands of years ago
formulate such a meticulously crafted
language that is perfect for computers
today also what religious texts should I
read if I haven't read any what is the
best English translations okay let's
let's um there are lots of questions in
here let's talk about Sanskrit yeah how
can I learn some certified country read
or write Hindi well Sanskrit the the
Sanskrit is a language and the medium in
which it is written is now that they
would not agree the script that they
have an ugly script in the past it was
written in various other scripts most
likely the Sindhu Sarasota script then
the Brahma script then also the Karishma
script then the Sharda script lots and
lots of scripts have been used to write
Sanskrit today the primary script is the
Deva nagari script so if you want to
learn Sanskrit you need to learn the
devanagar script you can do it in
four hours
and then you practice for a week you'll
become very comfortable with the Devon
architecture there's no big deal
learning a script is no big deal I
I remember as a kid
as a kid as a college kid I remember one
day I had nothing to do I was bored I
picked out a dictionary that are not
heavier it's called the American
Heritage American Heritage dictionary I
went to a random page it opened on the
Arabic script and I decided to learn the
Arabic script and within a couple of
hours I was able to start writing my
name and other things in the Arabic
script I now don't remember much of it
yeah because I haven't bothered to
practice
I think you can learn any script in a
matter of hours yeah especially one that
is intrinsically your own it's part of
your heritage so you need to learn the
devanagar script it will take you just a
matter of hours and with that you can
start learning Sanskrit now the question
is
what makes Sanskrit such an excellent
programming language well Sanskrit is
not a programming language a programming
language has a very limited
lexicon it needs a very limited number
of characters yep Sanskrit is not a
programming language it is not an
excellent programming language uh the
thing about Sanskrit is that it is a
very uh logical language it's almost
algorithmic in nature it has what we
call a completely formulated grammar
which is the ashtadi of Panini no other
natural language has this and it's the
only example of a generative grammar
yeah it's the only language it's the
only example among all the natural
languages that is that has a generative
grammar in contrast to other languages
which have a descriptive grammar right
so that's the difference between
Sanskrit and in other languages Sanskrit
is
a very uh
logical it has a very logical
algorithmic grammar it has a generative
grammar no other languages so a
generative grammar is one in which on
the basis of your very well established
lexicon and a set of very specific rules
the grammar can generate all
acceptable expressions of the language
and only those expressions of the
language which are acceptable yeah so
that is the thing about Sanskrit it's
got what we call the shabda both a
systematic method of analyzing the
meaning of any sentence yeah so that's
why we call Sanskrit a very it's it's
like a programming language but it's not
okay it's a natural it's a natural
language it doesn't quite have a context
specific grammar
the thing in machine translation see
these days we have Google translate
which is a machine translation we
translate from a source language to a to
a target language yeah the most
challenging application of uh natural
language processing which is machine
translation of source language to target
language is the logic the algorithm that
we use so when you have descriptive
grammars
it's very hard and that's why you see
lots of times that Google translate
doesn't do a very good job but when you
have a completely formulated grammar a
generative grammar then it becomes
trivial for a machine translation system
to translate accurately only Sanskrit
has that and that is something and and
the in the works of Parini are the well
the foundation of all Linguistics today
Panini in the even in the west is
recognized as the father of linguistics
so that is the reason why many people
believe that uh Sanskrit is an excellent
program in language no it's not since it
cannot be used as a programming image of
course you can use Sanskrit expressions
and terms in a programming language
instead of your uh Latin script that you
use in in let's say python in Python
syntax you could use an agree script and
Sanskrit words in that you could use
that that's one that's that's quite easy
to do yeah but it's not a programming
language but it's an extremely logical
language it's perfectly logical 100
logical there is no ambiguity yeah the
systematic method of analyzing and of
parsing a language a sentence and
analyzing this precise meaning of the
sentence that only Sanskrit has so
that's why people say that people have
the belief that is a wonderful
programming language it is not quite
that but it is
the the most scientific the most
algorithmic the most precise language
out there with the uh with with the most
Superior gamma if you want to if you
want to call it that yeah
uh is it very similar to Greek and Latin
no it's not
Greek and Latin have I mean we have a
whole bunch of languages which are
called the Indo-European language family
Sanskrit is the oldest of them all so
yeah all of these languages share some
similarities with Sanskrit but if you
speak Greek it doesn't mean you will be
able to understand any Sanskrit at all
yeah not necessarily or Latin
and Greek and Latin aren't as precise as
as Sanskrit right like I said the
Sanskrit has a completely formulated
grammar and a generative grammar Greek
and Latin don't have that so these are
all languages that are that all emerged
out of the old language which may have
been pretty Vedic Sanskrit yeah but it
is the classical Sanskrit of Panini that
has these characteristics that no other
language in human knowledge in human in
existence or in world history have
that's why we call Sanskrit Deva Basha
perhaps the language of the Gods yeah
foreign
[Music]
is definitely older than 2000 BC
so in the ramayan there are mentions of
the Saraswati like you mentioned like
you say and in the Mahabharata also
there are mentions of the river
Saraswati
we know that the Saraswati dried out
about 1500 or so BC most of it dried out
by that time 1500 BC that's three and a
half thousand years before today we also
know the river Saraswati started
declining in in strength in intensity
and Power in volume after about
5000 BC so the Indian Monsoon used to be
really heavy in the past but beginning
about 5000 BC the Indian Monsoon started
declining gradually and monotonically
gradual slow slow decline yeah over
centuries over thousands of years
so the river was last in her prime
around 7000 years before today
and she mostly dried out by about three
and a half thousand years before today
so this is a period of about three and a
half thousand years in which it went
from a full-fledged Great River to a
river that is half dried out or mostly
dried out yeah now
in the ramayan the Saraswati is
mentioned as a great River she is not
mentioned as a river that is in decline
or a river that is drying out which
means that the ramayana was written
closer to 7000 years before today
It Was Written closer to
I don't know what the date is I I forget
I think it's six thousand pieces which
means eight thousand years before today
so the ramayan was written closer to
that time when the river was in her
prime it was not written closer to 1500
BC when the river was mostly dried out
which means the ramayan is definitely
way way way older than 2000 BC
the ramayan could have been the events
of the ramayan could have happened maybe
somewhere around 5000 maybe 6000 BC
quite likely yeah but we don't have the
correct dates as of now it will happen
in the future we will get the dates
right now there's a lot of contention
confusion a lot of
uh all that yeah so we'll not go into
that controversy uh when it comes to the
Mahabharata it's it clearly uh mentions
the text clearly mentions the Saraswati
is a river that is declining that is
that is in the process of drying out
which means the Rama the Mahabharata was
written closer to 1500 BC but before
1500 BC yeah we don't know the exact
days it could have been 300 or 3000 BC
when the mahabara happened could have
been something else we don't know quite
what the date is various people have put
have proposed various dates and they are
very strongly adamant that my date is
correct everybody else is wrong I am not
getting into the controversy I have not
ever gone on record say to say that this
day dot is correct or that date is
correct so I have not uh taken any sides
in this but yeah to answer your question
the ramayan is way way way older than
2000 BC way before that
saurab again
sometimes I wonder about the ancient
Kings who lived during the Harappan
times across India and maybe some of our
Kings conquered Western lands but
unfortunately we don't have any
documents we have most of our documents
are gone burned in the destruction of
our great libraries drushila nananda
vikramshila uh and so on so forth we
have lost all of that information but we
still have the texts of the Rama and the
Mahabharata Etc in which especially in
the Mahabharat there are mentions of
extensive of many cities there are lots
of descriptions of pilgrimages and
travels and Journeys across India there
are descriptions of military campaigns
and there are mentions of many kingdoms
and cities yeah
so it would be interesting to try to uh
glean out parse out some descriptive
geographical information
the and then try to match it from what
we see from from the various uh
abandoned cities of that era that we do
have on the map
I'm sure nobody has bothered or tried to
do this seriously especially from an
academic perspective
I am sure that if if you if a you know
professors of history or academicians
were to try to do this and spend a few
years doing this I'm sure a lot of
correlations could be found between the
descriptions in these ancient texts and
the cities that we do know exist
in an abundant form on the map right the
various uh the various explored and
unexplored archaeological sites that we
know exist the thousands of them that do
exist I'm sure that if we do a proper
detailed systematic study we could be
able to start correlating some of these
places and putting actual names on these
cities that just exist as dots on the
map we don't even know what is the
original name of mohenjo daro or harappa
or rakhi gari or birana these are names
that have been given after the 19th and
20th Century yeah mohenjo daro means the
the mound of the Dead apparently
uh harappa I don't know what it means
but yeah these are Hindi names and so on
so we don't even know the true names of
these places what the people of that
time called those great cities
I think
if we do a proper systematic
investigation yeah using the best Minds
that we have at our disposal or some of
the best Minds we could be able to find
some actual you know put some names
on on some of the cities and if we are
able to identify some of the cities with
their actual names we may even be able
to know which Kings at some point ruled
over there and and so on it's it
certainly can be done it's just it's
just that our historians have never
bothered to do this because they are
busy doing something else
foreign
why is the Indus Valley Civilization
often portrayed as a very egalitarian
and non-violent Society good good
question there are plenty of evidences
of users of bronze weapons in the Indus
Valley how can we derive the conclusion
that lack of grandiose architecture and
equal symmetrical buildings suggests
that it was peaceful and egalitarian
pretty weak evidence in my opinion is
this a conclusion by British
archaeologists a consequence of
Communist Revolution in Russia during
the 1920s which had presented a very
tasteful Narrative of equality okay so
uh brah says see let's Analyze This
logically bro says that there is the
evidence that we have is pretty weak in
his opinion or her opinion
um
that uh the Saraswati Hindu civilization
was egalitarian and non-violent okay
let's let's be let's have an open mind
and be open to the possibility that
maybe it was not egalitarian and it was
maybe very violent or maybe there was
some violence yeah so let's ask
ourselves logically
are there any other examples in in the
archaeological record of civilizations
or cultures that have been known to be
in egalitarian and violent
yeah
so many
lots and lots of such examples Egypt is
an example Rome is an example uh the
yamnaya invasion of Europe there are so
many examples in in history there are
almost no examples of non-violent
societies almost all Societies in the
archaeological record are known to be
violent so then you ask yourself what
are the characteristics of a violent
Society you see evidence the
archaeological record of warfare of
battles of massacres you see that
everywhere you see arrowheads
strewn around in a battlefield you go to
hisarlik in Turkey in Anatolia and you
will see that the City of hazar Lake
has elements you know has as sections
uh chronological um
if you go if you look at the sedimentary
history yeah
so this stratigraphic history then you
will see a sections that there are there
is soot and Ash and you will find lots
of evidence of deaths in in the
arrowheads and broken swords and trees
and all that you go to ancient England
you will see very clear example evidence
in the archaeological record of the
Viking invasions yeah there is a there
are these Mass Graves that you find
where all the bones are in one place and
all the heads all the skulls are in a
different place which is clear evidence
of executions by decapitation yeah so we
know what violent societies look like in
the archaeological record
yes that is very that is not weak
evidence that is conclusive evidence do
you find any of that evidence anywhere
in the geographical uh range of the
Saraswati Hindu civilization you find
not one example of that do you call this
weak evidence
I know that the absence of evidence is
not evidence of absence we know that the
people of the Saraswati Sindhu region
and era
had armies how do we know this
we know this because of the records of
King Remus
of a card
he he fought a war against the people of
illum and marhashi and he records that
the kingdoms of ilam and mahashi were
had a military alliance with the people
of meluha is Hindu and the and there
were soldiers from who participated in
this war on the side of the people of
mahashi and and uh and ilam against the
arcadians so despite finding no evidence
of warfare in the Saraswati Hindu region
for thousands of years in the
archaeological record we know they had
soldiers
we know that the fought in wars and
geopolitical events outside of India
outside of the Indian subcontinent but
we find absolutely not a single shred of
evidence of warfare
or violence in any
of the services Hindu archaeological
sites in the future we may find
something thus far we have found nothing
I think that is extraordinarily strong
evidence yeah you get egalitarianism
okay what about inequality and all that
we love to see inequality in India right
what are examples of unequal societies
unequal societies have
in an unequal Society most of the
society's resources are controlled by a
very small minority of the population
the aristocracy the the the the nobility
whatever you want to call it right the
Warlords the Kings the Emperors you see
and we know Europe has always been like
this
we know that Rome was like that
we know that Egypt was like this and so
on we don't many other cultures that
have been like this and in all of these
unequal unequal societies and cultures
we find very specific characteristics of
inequality we find great palaces and
palaces that that uh
that uh are built by the rulers to keep
the the lower classes away and obviously
in various ways also
um
we see examples of monumental
architecture like the pyramids
the pyramids don't serve any social
purpose they serve the purpose of
glorifying the Kings and raising them to
the status of Gods
in this in the case of medieval Europe
ancient Europe we had the great palaces
and Forts and castles that showed off
the status of these people as way above
everybody else do you see any of these
things in the Saraswati Hindu region
in in that period of History the
so-called Harappan era or Indus Valley
you see none of that
you see none of that it's it's very
clear
over here it's not even absence of
evidence there's just nothing of that
kind
and all the great buildings serve social
purposes that serve the entire Society
the greatest buildings are meeting Halls
the great the largest buildings are
meeting halls or or communal baths or or
grain storage facilities and all that
which serve the society and the common
people
so once again I think it's very strong
evidence of a more egalitative in
society than what you see elsewhere
so that's what I have to say about this
obviously you can believe whatever you
like that is fine but we are talking
logic here we're not talking emotions
we're talking we are having this
conversation on the on the basis of the
evidence that is available to us here in
the Saraswati Sindhu region and outside
in the rest of the world there's a very
clear Contra distinction in the kind of
evidence we have in the archaeological
record which is why even the West phase
that the so-called Harappan civilization
was almost utopian no evidence of
Warfare no evidence of class divides all
that even they claim it even they have
to say it
that's what we are
rodrigit says you always say that once
the Central Asian people considered
India to be their ancestral home and
adored and followed Indian culture but
then how and when did they start
considering India a foreign place and
attacked India countless times thank you
see yes I have said this because we know
it it was so Madara
so uh and even in 19th century German
Maps you see the name
temporarily occupied by China
that was uttarakuru north of the
Himalayas north of the actual Guru
mahajanapada in India and Central Asia
Tajikistan
all of that Uzbekistan all of that was
called Madra
these were all we know it from the
archaeological record and other sources
that these kingdoms which which resulted
in these places were all Indian origin
kingdoms we all know that it is you read
in history textbooks of that and if you
look at the history of that period
it's more or less agreed yeah
now so what happened so these people
these are not Central Asian peoples
these were Indian origin people who had
gone out of India through wave after
wave of migrations yeah and some of them
became nomadic we we call them the Saka
people the Shaka people the West calls
themeshara people and other people who
were who were called the tokarians yeah
so what happened is the question what
happened is there were migrations from
other places
so uh the horns emerged out of uh
Eastern Eurasia north of China north of
Mongolia more or less the region of
Mongolia they were called the Chinese
called them the show new
they became a war like people they
overwhelmed everybody else which forced
these the kushans the the descendants of
the tushara people and the skitians the
Shaka people to migrate
westwards and southwards into India
which gave us the the skition uh
invasion of India and the question
invasion of India and they all
assimilated harmoniously because they
were of Indian origin the same culture
essentially the same people now the
horns took over Central Asia
they established their own Supremacy
they were a whole different ethnicity
the homes were a different ethnicity
let's put the map on because so that we
understand what's happening
um where is the map we're looking at
aini Air Base Let's uh
give me a second
let's see the map
to understand this better so we have
India we know where it is yeah present
day Tibet in so-called xinjiang was
uttara Kuru in Central Asia which is
north of Afghanistan
which is
now the horns they emerged out of
most likely east of Mongolia or Mongolia
itself present-day Mongolia at that time
it was not called Mongolia right
and they went they started sweeping
across Central Asia so the kushans
invaded India they were actually fleeing
from the homes and then they established
the an empire in India and over time
they assimilated into the Indian
population the sketheans also
assimilated into the Indian population
so did the the Indo Greeks now
so these Indian origin Kingdoms in
Central Asia were replaced by honik
kingdoms
right and the ethnicity also got mixed
because the homes were now the the
overlords of most of central Asia and
there would be intermixion intermixing
of the Indian origin people and the
honig people in Central Asia then
you had the hones eventually they they
reached Europe they also invaded India
parts of India we know that the hunic
invasions of India the shweta hunas and
then you had the turkic supremacy Awards
Indonesia so
the Turks most likely were of hunnic
origin but they became islamized and
then there were New Waves of invasions
um and they destroyed the Indian origin
Heritage of Central Asia you will see
ruins of of uh
Hindu temples and Buddhist stupas and
monasteries all across Central Asia some
of them have been replaced by uh
religious structures of the the religion
of the of the Turks yeah but all of that
was replaced and the Turks were again a
different ethnicity they killed off most
of the men
of the original inhabitants of Central
Asia and they took the women as slaves
and that gave rise to a mixed race of
people who now inhabit Central Asia and
who have no connection anymore to Indian
culture
that's why
they started attacking India and that's
what that's the history that's how it
goes
so if you look at the people of Central
Asia today
they may have a little bit of Indian
ancestry but if you look at the people
the population of Central Asia 2000
years ago they would have 80 Indians in
the street that's what happened
so Indian ancestry was wiped out towards
a significant extent and Indian culture
was almost entirely wiped out from
Central Asia it's more about culture
than DNA always remember
always remember culture matters DNA
doesn't matter
yeah
that is what happened
okay again
we know that in ancient times many
Indians went to Southeast Asia for trade
and intermitted with the natives there
and established many indianized kingdoms
can you name in some of those kingdoms
and shares of their history okay I'll
just give a couple of names and names
because otherwise you can have a
six-month University level course on
this not six months you can have a
two-year course on this it's extremely
uh detailed history very interesting
history yeah so let's take a look at
some of that
once again I'm going to put Wikipedia on
the screen as always please understand
please realize Wikipedia is not always
not necessarily reliable especially when
it comes to Indian history
but I am just putting it on the screen
for the sake of convenience for the sake
of giving a very brief overview one of
the kingdoms we are talking about was
funan okay funan was in uh Southern
Vietnam Southern Cambodia uh the
ancestors essentially of the Khmer
people
so funan kingdom was one of these uh it
was an indianized State a network of
states or a mandala located in in
Mainland Southeast Asia
uh so funan goes back to about 2000
years before today uh the first queen or
the first ruler of Hunan was Queen Soma
she is claimed to be the first monarch
of Cambodia she was the consort the wife
of kondinia
uh
was an Indian person an Indian merchant
ship was attacked by Pirates led by Soma
the daughter of the chieftain of the
local Naga Clan the entire story is
there you can read it up read it up if
you want so who was going the India
let's take a look at who Conde was
um
it was the second monarch of Hunan he
was the husband of of Queen Soma
um
and he
he was from odisha he was from Kalinga
we we call it odisha today so we know
that Kalinga had extensive and very
ancient trade trade relationship
relations with southeast Asia at least
for the past 3000 years even 3000 years
ago merchants and sailors from from
Kalinga from Eastern India were
traveling by ship
across the present day what's now called
the Bay of Bengal the Kalinga Sagar into
southeast Asia in trading there so one
of these people was a merchant
apparently a brahmana from Kalinga and
he went to this place uh present-day
Cambodia in Vietnam he married the local
princess queen princess Soma the queen
Soma and they gave rise to the funan
kingdom so this is about 2000 years
before today right so that's the story
of of Hunan Kingdom the successor state
of of funan was called chinla the
Chinese call it chinla this was again
Hindu yeah uh and the successor of that
essentially is the kingdom of Champa
that again goes back almost 2000 years
it was in existence from 190 to 80 to
1832 A.D almost to almost 1900 years
almost 2000 years roughly yeah give or
take
and uh the the uh what is now called the
South China Sea was historically called
the Champa Sagar the Sea of Champa the
champasi yep so the the the kingdom or
Empire of Champa was again an indianized
hinduise Kingdom yeah
a mostly shy white Kingdom you will find
lots of shiver temples in this region uh
when you obviously cannot uh neglect to
talk about Java Indonesia Java again has
a 2000 plus year old Indian Hindu
history uh the main island was yabadweep
and heard so many of these rulers uh
Deva varman
Purna Verma
Maharaja
Queen Shema so they had their culture
was very much Indian they had Queens
they had Kings women got women could
also become the ruler of the country
just as in India in other cultures you
will never see that yeah
dynasty was a very significant Dynasty
yeah uh
it still rules srivajiya in Sumatra
and and so much it's a very extensive
history it's almost impossible to talk
about it in in just a few minutes there
are so many kingdoms and so many
dynasties
um the majapahit empire was the was the
Imperial phase of the of of Indonesia it
was a Hindu phase obviously it was the
greatest it was the most glorious phase
of Indonesia's history there's still
remember that with with great fondness
and they consider the people of
Indonesia consider that to be the
Pinnacle of Indonesian history uh and so
on so there's a whole
it's an enormous amount of History to
unpack there's a good book by RC
majumdar I believe an old book but that
throws a lot of light on on the
indianized kingdoms he calls it colonies
or whatever for whatever reason he he
wrote this in a different era when they
thought about everything as a colony but
yeah those were indianized kingdoms
those were not colonies of India of
India in Southeast Asia
and of course this extends Way Beyond
southeast Asia uh even the Philippines
had indianized kingdoms some of their
kings had Chola ancestry yeah and this
continued until the Portuguese
destruction of of
Philly of the Philippines and their
culture and then the Philippines were
christianized forcibly by the Portuguese
so you had uh Indian culture all across
southeast Asia all the way to the
Philippines and of course in in in in
Thailand in Burma uh Thailand and Burma
were called suvarna bhumi even two and a
half thousand years before today yeah
and of course in China in in Korea all
the way up to Japan and of course
westwards also very very very detailed
and involved history but I I hope I've
thrown a little bit of light on this and
evoked hopefully some curiosity from
those of you who are interested in this
so look it up check out RC majumdar's
book on on this period of Southeast
Asian history and there are lots of
online articles also that you can use
for or reading more about this
samrat says Buddha was born in Nepal sir
look
if you want to say that Buddha was born
in labor have you heard of Hannibal
Hannibal Barka
Hannibal Barca was a carthaginian
general
uh and he fought against Rome very
successfully may I say
so Hannibal was from Carthage where is
Carthage found today the ruins of
Carthage are found near the present-day
city of Tunis you can see Carthage here
it's it's all ruins the Romans destroyed
Carthage eventually yeah
must be destroyed so that happened
afterwards but Hannibal Barca was one of
the greatest generals of Carthage he
invaded Rome yeah Rome present Italy
very successfully so you could claim
from that perspective
you could claim that Hannibal was
Tunisian
would it be accurate to claim that
Hannibal was Tunisian because Carthage
is located in present-day Tunisia it's
it's ridiculous to say that Hannibal
Barca was Tunisian
yeah that's wrong and similarly it's
kind of ridiculous to not kind of it's
very ridiculous to say
that lord karna of the Mahabharata era
was a Bangladeshi
yes he ruled over angadesh which is now
West Bengal and Bangladesh historical
Bengal but is it right to call Lord
karna a Bangladeshi or a Bengali
is it it's not
similarly
the the present-day nation state of
Nepal
originates in the Kingdom of Nepal
which goes back to the times of prithvi
Narayan Shah so when did he live 1700s I
believe
so between let me Google it I don't
remember dates please okay don't so
don't mind it
when did he live
1700s so he established the kingdom of
nevar which is now called Nepal that's
just 300 or so years ago there was no
Nepal before that the region always
existed it was always part of various
kingdoms of Indian kingdoms and Indian
Empires it was part of the kushan Empire
it was part of the mauryan Empire it was
part of various other Empires it was
part of the Gupta Empire as well and so
many empires it was part of various
mahajanapadas of India it was always
Indian there was no Nepal before the
1700s
the nation state the kingdom of Nepal
originates in the conquests of prithvi
narayansha in that small region in the
1700s before that there was no concept
of a kingdom of Nepal in the nation
state of Nepal came much later
so just like Hannibal Barca was not
Tunisian just like King karna of the
Mahabharata was not Bangladeshi
similarly Lord Buddha was not Nepalese
of course
you many of you may not agree that's
fine logic and emotions are hold to
different things
and they should not they should not be
mixed but well there we go
ah science Karan says how does a black
hole evaporate and where does it
evaporate and why does it evaporate
see black holes have temperature
a black hole has a temperature it's
called the Hawking temperature and any
object that has a temperature which is
hot
any hot object radiates it radiates
so black holes radiate uh
black body radiation they radiate
particles that in radiation that form
the black body Spectrum
and
the temperature of a black hole it's
called the hooking temperature
and because of the temperature there is
a certain rate at which a black hole
emits radiation
the hotter the black hole is the faster
it emits radiation and the smaller black
hole is the hotter it is yeah
so there is a certain rate at which a
black hole emits radiation it's
proportional to the inverse of the
square of the mass of the black hole one
upon M squared proportional to one upon
M squared m is the mass of the black
hole so the smaller black hole the
faster it emits radiation and this is
called evaporation so that's how it
happens now what's inside a black hole
we don't quite know we can approximate
we can construct a theoretical black
hole from the perspective of quantum
mechanics using by by approximating a
black hole is a bag of let's say
photons you can even
we can even construct a black hole as a
bag of of strings a fuzzball whatever
and you can play around with the match
but black holes evaporate because they
are hot they have a temperature the
smaller black hole is the hotter it is
and the faster it evaporates or emits
radiation and eventually it explodes
into nothingness and where does it
evaporate it evaporates right where it
is
assuming it's a short skilled
non-rediating non-rotaining black hole
it's going to be completely spherical
it's going to uh evaporate which means
emit radiation all around its
surroundings and it will go go outside
outwards that's how it goes yeah
the madman the madman says can a
collision of two neutron stars create
gravitational waves how are the
gravitational waves even detected a
collision of anything creates
gravitational waves so when two neutron
stars collide they're gonna give rise
not gravitational waves but
gravitational tsunami in enormous
gravitational wave when two black holes
Collide they're going to give rise to a
gravitational wave tsunami it's not a
small wave it's a it's a it's a huge
tsunami enormous enormous wave with an
enormous amplitude yeah and even when
there's a black hole versus Neutron Star
Collision there is a gravitational wave
or tsunami that is emitted even when I
punch my palm with my fist that way
that's gonna give off gravitational
waves but those are gonna be very small
tiny tiny ripples in the fabric of
space-time when I do this it just emits
in incredibly small ripples
ripples in the fabric of space-time but
when two enormous massive objects
Collide it creates it creates a huge
tsunami in the fabric of space-time and
today the gravitational wave detectors
that we have are only able to detect
enormous tsunamis they can't detect
small ripples on the fabric of
space-time so how are gravitational
waves detected
um
the instrument that we have is called
Lego uh soon and uh an Indian version of
Lego is going to come up it's going to
be called Indigo what's uh what is legal
like uh Lego essentially is a gravity is
is a Michelson interferometer let me uh
put that on the screen what that is uh
let's quickly do this
Lego essentially is an enormous mic
that's what it is so it has two arms
which are at right angles to each other
this is the essential schematic yeah and
uh the uh the
arms are very long several kilometers
long yeah
and what and the the light is crossed
and if if there is a if if the two paths
the two parts are in the the distance
between the two uh of the lengths of the
two arms are exactly equal yeah and if a
gravitational waves if a gravitational
wave uh is incident on this apparatus
then there's going to be torsion it's
going to twist the fabric of space-time
and then what what the consequence of
that is that the lengths of the two arms
become unequal and that's going to give
rise to interference fringes in the
laser light that is that is being uh
split and then recombined yeah so that
is the basic uh basic uh
the basic construction of the Lego
interferometer so ligo is extremely
extremely sensitive it can detect a very
small change it can detect a change in
the distance between its mirrors which
is about one ten thousandth of the width
of a proton
a proton is a subatomic particle which
is found inside most atoms inside all
atoms sorry yeah even the hydrogen atom
has a nucleus which is a proton so the
legal detector can detect a change in
distance between its mirrors
which which is as small as one ten
thousandth the width of a proton which
is equivalent to measuring the distance
between
between Earth and the nearest star Alpha
Centauri which is about
4.2 light years away measuring the
distance to an accuracy smaller than the
width of a human error
so that's the kind of thing it is
and that's why we are able to detect uh
gravitational waves I believe about 90
or so gravitational waves have been
detected thus far and there are various
um runs that ligo goes through thus far
we have detected about 90 or so the
first one was I believe in 2015 and
there was a momentous occasion in the
history of experimental physics
right
lots of questions by our friend I have
noticed that nowadays people are showing
so much attraction for Chinese Korean
and Japanese culture but people don't
seem to be much interested or attracted
to Indian culture which is a huge impact
on the previous mentioned cultures what
which has had a huge impact on these
other cultures that you have mentioned
yeah it's what's your take on this yeah
it's it's true
um why are people showing so much
well why are people so attracted it's
because of the media it's because of the
entertainment industry it's because of
Hollywood and then Indian Indian
Entertainment copies Hollywood
that's what Indian Entertainment
entertainment does if you look at all
the various entertainment uh shows like
Indian Idol or whatever they are copying
shows that were started in the West
Indian Idol is a knockoff of American
Idol Indian music today is a knockoff of
American music or or western music A.R
Rahman in the 1990s started using
electronic instruments and copying
western music and Indian saw it's a very
huge Innovation and then Bollywood
started copying that and today you don't
have any Indian instruments or Indian
Styles left in Bollywood in mainstream
music anymore this was all started by
A.R Rahman by aping Western music by
using electronic instruments which were
imported from the west and and
and much of the influence comes from
Hollywood now Hollywood is very
I think I've said this before see if if
you look very it's Hollywood if you
watch various Hollywood movies they will
glorify and celebrate cultures from
across the world
take a look at various Pixar movies like
Moana for instance Moana celebrates
Polynesian culture if you watch the the
Pixar or Disney movie I don't know which
it is Coco Coco which came recently it
celebrates indigenous Mexican Aztec
culture of the Day of the Dead yeah Dio
this Muertos or whatever it is if you
watch Aladdin it celebrates Arabian
Arabic culture if you watch Mulan it
celebrates Chinese culture if you watch
the latest mummy movie The Mummy it
celebrates Chinese culture the original
mummy movie celebrates Egyptian culture
the wakanda movie celebrates African
culture
uh if you watch Avatar the first Avatar
movie it celebrates to an extent Native
American culture indigenous culture if
you watch movies like The Last of the
Mohicans the dances of Dances with
Wolves it celebrates Native American
culture
in 1972 there was a meeting between uh
President Nixon of the U.S and and Mao
the dictator of China
and Mao and Nixon decided to open up
China to American Investment into
American influence the next tier entered
the Enter the Dragon was released in
Chinese culture became a hit in the west
yeah
if you watch shows like Silicon Valley
there's this character called Dinesh
who's one of the main characters in
Silicon Valley he's depicted as a
Pakistani yeah not Indian if you watch
movies like Thor Thor love and love and
summer love and thunder something you
have all the gods in the in the world
who are depicted in this one scene the
pantheon of gods from across the world
but no Indian gods and they show Zeus
and Thor as separate Gods when actually
they are the same God
and of course we have the celebration of
Japanese culture Japanese anime manga we
have a celebration of K-pop in in the
western world but you never see any
celebration of Indian culture ever
why is that because all the other
cultures that are celebrated are
defeated cultures these are cultures
that have been defeated by the West
in 1972 they considered considering
China also to be a definite culture
because China were first forced to open
up to the U.S
because they were facing great threats
from the USSR yeah dating back to the
1960s
so they see China as a defeated culture
and of course there's a lot to money a
lot of money to be made from China so
they celebrate Chinese culture and all
the other cultures I specified are all
cultures the West considers to be
defeated cultures
it's only India that is thus far not
been defeated in the past 1000 Years
Indian culture has refused to die
that's why they refuse to celebrate
Indian culture any depiction of Indian
culture 1960s onwards is going to be
negative in the west if it is at all
ever depicted and what's funny is that
there are many people in the west who
practice
what you could call Hinduism yeah but
they are always depicted as Buddhists
take the example of Tina Turner
she is depicted as a Buddhist take the
example of Steve Jobs you go to
Wikipedia and search for Steve Jobs
they're going to portray him as a
Buddhist they will say he practiced Zen
Buddhism do you know that when Steve
Jobs died he had a picture of the of the
Indian Hindu Guru neem karoli Baba on
his bedstead bedstead he had a blanket
of name karoli Baba with him and he had
a book called Miracle of love which is a
collection of stories and teachings
about names right next to him when he
died
so clearly he was influenced by a Hindu
Guru then he and he believed in what we
call Hinduism and yet he is depicted as
a Buddhist yeah uh so that's how it is
it's big there is there is a blanket
whitewashing and and omission of of any
representation or representation of
Indian culture in Western media in the
western entertainment world complete
blanket
deletion that they just don't show it or
if they show it they show it in a very
negative manner Slumdog whatever the
movie was extremely negative portrayal
of India if you look at the news it's
all negative any mention of Indian
culture is negative there is a there is
this
Festival in in Northern in Nepal I
believe in which the slaughter buffaloes
and maybe on in in one day the slaughter
maybe a few thousand buffaloes so that
is Portrait as incredibly barbaric do
you know how many millions or billions
of cattle are slaughtered in an
extremely inhumane way in North America
what is the ritual sacrifice of 5000
buffaloes compared to that
and yet they portrait this is extremely
primitive and barbaric but what the West
does is beautiful so these are the
reasons why because of the complete
absence of any depiction or
representation of Indian culture in the
entertainment industrial media and
whatever is there is negative that's why
people are now they now feel especially
in India that Indian culture is inferior
is primitive they are ashamed of of
speaking about Indian culture then they
try to to copy the West to imitate the
west and that's why they are very
attracted to whatever is shown in a
positive light like Chinese culture or
Korean culture or Japanese culture or
whatever else it is brainwashing
through suggestion
yeah
that's how it is
and today you see yeah okay let's not go
there that's enough
all right let's what else shall we take
Daniel says what which countries have
the right to mine lunar minerals and
metals do nations with lunar missions
have exclusive rights to those things or
will those be shared with interested
Nations as well look at past history
NASA NASA went to the moon they brought
back several kilos of kilos of moon
rocks
who owns those moon rocks they own it do
they share it with anybody else they may
share with certain Nations those who are
their vasals have they shared any of
that with India I'm not sure I don't
think so
um the Chinese recently went to the moon
they sent a Changi Brewer to the Moon
they I think they brought back some some
samples or they may be in the process of
bringing like samples those are
exclusively Chinese so which nations
have the right to mine lunar minerals
and materials and metals those who can
reach there
yeah no one can stop them and they they
have they are under no obligation of
sharing that to share that with anybody
else that's why I keep saying India
needs to ensure it becomes one of the
major space-faring nations in the 21st
century yeah it is extremely important
it is essential that India does it India
should not be left behind in the space
race
yeah because space is the next Frontier
space is like the same Star Trek the
final frontier
all right uh let's take a couple more
questions
my goodness how many questions
um the land of Lord Shiva in one of the
holiest places for all dharmic uh paths
is currently occupied by China is it not
shameful it is unacceptable in this
situation will be rectified not far from
today it has to be rectified it does not
belong in anyone's hands except those
who who respect the Army culture Tibet
is fine but not China
mother says how to handle failure I
attempted a civil services example exam
similar to upsc a couple of months ago
the results came out a few days ago and
I couldn't I just couldn't make it by a
small margin any advice
see look at take a look at the people
you admired the most the most successful
people in the world I can guarantee you
that the people who are now considered
to be the most successful people in the
world have failed more times than any
average person
you cannot succeed without learning from
failure but only if you can learn from
failure constructively so how to handle
failure take it first of all take it as
a learning experience secondly you
should not have only one option in life
you place all your eggs in one basket if
it doesn't work you doomed it should not
be like that you should have multiple
backup options
let's say your upsc was plan A
you should also have plan B plan C Plan
D and in the long run what you make in
the long run life is long
life is really long you you because of
today's
advances in medical technology and all
that most people I think now can expect
to live 100 years if they are reasonably
lucky and if they take good care of
themselves so let's say you fail at
something in your 20s it should not
dishearten or discourage you there's a
lot more you can do in your life you
have a long long life ahead of you so
always have multiple options multiple
plans always know you have to first
understand yourself and what you are
best at what you will be good at in life
have a 10-year objective
break it up into a five year into five
year objectives and a one-year objective
and whatever your one year objective is
you should have quarterly objectives
also and you should have multiple goals
not just one goal if you fail at one
thing learn from it but don't be
discouraged and that should not be the
end of everything you should always have
backup plans so that's how you handle
failure failure is an opportunity to
learn if you analyze why whatever
happened happened why did it happen What
were the the the steps you took that
could have contributed to your whatever
you call failing yeah so that's what you
do
so always have multiple backup plans
always have a big goal and if it doesn't
work this way we'll do it that way
that's how we do it so be positive
understand you've got a long life learn
from the best
people that you admire I can guarantee
each of them failed more times than most
people will ever fail in in one life
that's how it goes so it's all about
learning
and always keep on advancing and always
have multiple plans that's what you do
all the best sir all the best
um
Mingo says I want to know how your brain
stores so many facts and information any
secrets and please do more science
podcasts I don't know I just have access
to one brain and it is the way it is I
don't know whether it's I don't think
I've memorized lots of stuff I I what I
see is patterns and you can only see
patterns if you go through a lot of
information so you're going to read a
lot I read you can watch podcasts you
can learn in any way you want I don't
think I store lots of facts and
information or I only store what I find
interesting and that's what I talk about
I don't talk about things I don't find
interesting so uh I don't know I don't
know what secrets are there for me
there's no secret I'm just who I am I've
always been this way uh I don't think I
am great at memorizing stuff I forget
lots of things I have to Google it
specific names and dates and all that I
forget that all the time but I overall
understand the big picture so that's how
it works for me
um please do more science podcasts I
think this year I'm going to do way more
spine science podcasts this year
starting the coming week itself yeah
this may be the year of science on this
channel of course other things as well
but I'm gonna reorient my focus more
towards science to a certain some extent
this year yeah
is human body symmetrical my right hand
is slightly bigger than the left one
[Laughter]
um
listen no human
right versus left say listen no human
body is perfectly symmetrical okay if if
a body is perfectly symmetrical it's
unnerving to see that it doesn't happen
it doesn't happen in nature right hand
left hand right foot left foot whatever
is lie right left
yes you're always going to have some
asymmetry even in the human face yeah so
don't worry if your one hand is bigger
one is smaller it's It's Perfectly
Natural you can never have perfect
symmetry anywhere
um Ronald Raj menu says where did this
suckers and kittens go where did you
take them please give them back before
the date of third January this kitchens
are in my custody and they are not going
anywhere is what it is
okay let's briefly take some questions
from um
from the live chat briefly five minutes
do we have any questions from from the
live chat
um
why does the Chism have a caste system
we wanted for those made to counter
causes them Sikhism was not made to
counter any alleged caste system in
Hinduism Sikhism is very much very much
part of Hinduism
sikhi came out of a desire to evict
the foreign occupiers of India out of
India it was a more militaristic
uh path that certain Indians took Hindus
I don't see any difference between
the real psychicism and and any other
dharmic pant or path of of India
yeah and so so that's it so the belief
that Sikhism was made to counter the
caste system is absolutely ridiculous
Sikhism or sikhi it's per its sole
purpose was to free India liberate India
from the foreign occupies the brutal
barbarians who are destroying India and
destroying Indian culture and committing
a genocide in India that was the only
objective of sikhi not to reform Indian
Society or or counter some imaginary
caste system or any of that please
understand this yeah so yeah
uh right
um let's see
how many failures have I had in my
career plenty plenty and here I am
everybody fails in lots of things what's
the big deal you've got to learn and
you've got to move on yeah so
most people will fail at multiple things
and it's perfectly fine perfectly fine
but the main thing is keep going forward
keep working hard and stay positive
all right what else do we have
ID cases Pakistan Taliban created
another government in Pakistan how will
it affect Pakistan India so they've set
up a parallel government Shadow
government it's going to be interesting
times for Pakistan how would it affect
India
it will not affect India negatively
that's much what I'm that's how much I
can tell you
uh
how can we say that Earth is tilted when
it is in space and no base below it it
is not deleted with respect to up or
down it is tilted like this with respect
to the plane of the solar system
the solar system you can think of it is
a is a flat disc more or less so if you
look at the flat disc of the solar
system all the planets in objects
essentially go around the Sun in the
same plane more or less you take that
plane and then you see the inclination
of the the rotation of the earth it's
inclined with respect to that plane that
is what we mean when we say that the
Earth is tilted all right
right anything else
um
is the was the early Harappan
civilization a contemporary of the
Mahabharata era I think there was
definitely some kind of overlap between
the Saraswati Sindhu phase of Indian
history and the Mahabharata Iraq yeah
but we don't know exactly what it was
because we don't know the date exact
date or even the Millennium in which the
Mahabharata happened like I said lots of
people have put up claims I am not
favoring any claim yeah but I am it's
pretty much sure that the Saraswati
Hindu phase of Indian history was
contemporaneous with with some part of
it was contemporaneous
all right
[Music]
um
what else what else what else
Ian says how to manage time and mobile
addiction if you have big objectives
that that obsess you
if you have a big tenure goal and you
have a big five-year goal which is part
of the 10-year goal and if you have a
big 2023 goal and if you are really
invested in that if you're really
obsessed with that you will not have the
time to look at your mobile phone and
waste time here and there you'll be
working towards that because it really
matters to you it means something to you
something very important to you you need
to have that you need to have some kind
of obsession in life without that you're
gonna waste your time I I mean yeah I
don't even have the time to watch
podcasts so you need to have something
like that then it's not an issue you
will not even want to look at the mobile
phone and scroll up like people do all
the time and all that yeah and time
management is an art it's it's something
that takes time to learn the main thing
is don't have too many tasks in a day
only have
your real work is like three four hours
a day maximum where you can really focus
so that is something you can split
across only one or two tasks so in a day
you should have maybe three main tasks
three main things you're working on and
everything else should not be given as
much importance as you otherwise would
so be focused and and you need to evolve
your own system of time management
obviously there are lots of different
ways of doing it you can read about it
various various books or see it on
online
various methods various systems there is
something called time boxing there are
other things as well so yeah you've got
to find what suits you best everybody is
different everybody will be able to
manage time
optimally in different ways
huh all right
what else we have
um
our brahman's Jews as said by something
bam bamsaf what I don't know who says
that but those people need to have their
heads examined whoever it is I don't
know what damn self or whatever else is
but yeah
okay I think we are done for today two
hours ten minutes so we're gonna end the
session today over here thank you as
always for all the wonderful questions
very interesting questions always that I
get some very new ones yeah so yeah
thank you and I wish you a very
successful and happy 2023 and I will see
you in next week's live streams and
we're gonna do some podcasts as well and
we're going to focus on science a little
more this year so uh thank you very much
take care and I will see you very soon
in the next live stream bye